<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise, concerning the vse and abuse of dauncing. Collected oute of the learned workes of the most excellent deaine doctour, Peter Martyr, by paister Rob Massonius: and translated into English by I.K.</title>
            <author>Vermigli, Pietro Martire, 1499-1562.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide G.1999[3]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892568</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892568</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183665</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183665)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; B1:1[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise, concerning the vse and abuse of dauncing. Collected oute of the learned workes of the most excellent deaine doctour, Peter Martyr, by paister Rob Massonius: and translated into English by I.K.</title>
                  <author>Vermigli, Pietro Martire, 1499-1562.</author>
                  <author>I. K.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[54] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Iohn Iugge, dwellyng at the north doore of Paules,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1580?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dancing --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A briefe Treatiſe, <hi>Concerning the vſe and</hi>
abuſe of Dauncing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Collected oute of the</hi> learned workes of the moſt
excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Deuine Doctour, <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> by Maiſter <hi>Rob.
Maſsonius:</hi> And tranſlated into Engliſh by</hi> I. K.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſti. 9. ver. 4.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>¶ Vſe not the company of a vvoman that is a ſynger, and a
dauncer: neither heare her, leaſt thou be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by her
craftineſſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>by</hi> Iohn Iugge, <hi>dwellyng
at the North doore of Poules.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:2"/>
            <head>To the ryght worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Maister Alexander</hi> Nowell,
Deane of the Cathedrall Church <hi>of Saint</hi> Paul: <hi>Happie health with
grace from God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing (right</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypfull) a Treatiſe ſent vnto
mee to be Imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as touching the vſe and abuſe of dauncing: Collected
out of the works of the moſt worthie, and wel learned Deuine Doctour,
<hi>Peter Martir.</hi> I fancied to preſent the ſame (eſpeciallie and
aboue the reſt) to your worshyp and worthie perſon, onely enforced thereto
by the common brute of your rare zeale, ſingular vertue, and godly
Religion.</p>
            <p>The partie by whoſe penne and paine it was tranſlated, and
chaunged from Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine robe, to English veſture, is both vertuous, learned,
and godlie: and being ſtirred, as it were ſtinged foreward of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie zeale,
ſeeing theſe diſordred and daly daunſings in the rude Countrey, marring
mennes manners, breeding much beaſtly <pb facs="tcp:183665:3"/> behauiour: and being
deſirous to haue ſuch rudeneſſe reformed in thoſe quarters where he
is acquainted, requeſted and wyld me to procure in print the publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
thereof: VVhich hauing accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plished, I moſt humbly preſent the ſame to
your vvorshyppe, emboldned the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnder your name to haue it publish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and put forth in print, to the vew of the worlde, for that it hath bene
ouerloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and lyked of Diuines, zealous, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, learned, and godly.
VVherfore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring you good Maſter <hi>Nowell,</hi> ſo it may bee taken
as a token of my good wyll to your vvorshyppe: I forbeare any farther to
moleſt you with my vnlettered lynes, beſeching the euer and ouer ruling
<hi>Iehoua</hi> through his Chriſt Ieſus our only ioy, to continue his good
bleſsings vpon you, and to make perfect the good he hath begunne in you, and
in vs all. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>¶<hi>Your vvorshippes to commaund.
T.K.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>To the Chriſtian <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I, who am as</hi> I am. Vndertake this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (good
Chriſtian) when other of our Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wryting both learnedly with
iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and zealouſly with knowledge, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diuerſe and ſundry
abuſes crept in amongſt vs, nothing or very lytle handle the ſame, may to
many perhaps, who are lyghtly wayed to the worſe parte, offer occaſion of
this common obiection: What meaneth he to medle with this thing, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee
ſéeth others holde their peace? what? thinketh he if it were ſo
neceſſarie and néedefull a thing to bée publiſhed in print,
that among ſo many Bookes, there ſhoulde bée none, or nothing in
them ſet foorth? This kinde of cauell, becauſe I ſée it firſt
&amp; moſt of all others in the mouthes of many, it ſéemed not
therefore to mée a myſſe at the firſt to méete herewith:
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to remoue the ſiniſter opinion they conceaue (I dare ſay) of
the godly, as alſo the preiudiciall verdite this maye bréede 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:4"/> vppon this my true, though not trimme ſtyle of wryting. Whether
there bée not diuerſe that haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fréely &amp; franklie
againſt the abuſe of Dauncing, not onely in the Latin and French, but
likewiſe in our mother tongue: who wyll plucke the beame out of his eyes,
maye ſoone eſpie. But why our late learned men haue not purpoſely penned
ſome péece of work, (if it be long agoe or lytle, theſe men forget
it, or neuer ſée it) foraſmuch as it may be imputed to the want,
neyther of wyll nor abilitie, to what it maye bee, I certainly know not: for
who knoweth what things are in man, ſauing God and the ſpirit in him) yet
to vſe a probable coniecture, I take the occaſion to be in theſe vertuous
perſons: Becauſe God hath eyther geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peaceable ſtate of
<hi>Salomon,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they néede not come forth into the fielde: or if
not the peaceable ſtate, yet the ready yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the people vnder
<hi>EZra,</hi> that there required no aſſaulte to be geuen: or if not the
ready yéelding, yet the ſpeedy conqueſt of captaine
<hi>Ioſua,</hi> that the onely certayne ſounde of the Trumpe, the
ſcripture hath ouerthrowne the walles of <hi>Iericho:</hi> and the walles
ouerthrown, the bright Lamps <pb facs="tcp:183665:4"/> of the goſpell ſo ſhined out of
their earthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veſſelles, that the eyes of the aduerſaries wer in ſuch
ſort daſeled, that <hi>Phineas</hi> with his ſpeare thruſt this
<hi>Madianitishe</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man cleane thorow: or if none of all theſe come to
paſſe, (as oft times for the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of our iniquityes in theſe
latter dayes they doo not) yet becauſe God hath ſent them a
<hi>Moyſes</hi> zelouſe in his cauſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi>
32.19</note> to put downe ſuch outragious paſtime, that theyr ſhoulders
are eaſed of this heauye burthen. But wyll ſome <hi>Saloms</hi> ſay, this
compariſon you make betwéene vs, &amp; the chyldren of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> is odious. Farre bée it from vs, that our diſporte
ſhould be lyke, or lykened vnto theyre. Whether there be ſuch diſſolute
diſportes in all places or no, I am vtterly ignoraunt, and God for byd there
ſhoulde: Neyther include I in this my compariſon all manner of daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, no
more then mine Author doth, and ſo I beſéeche thée (gentle
Reader) inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete both our meanings. But truely to reporte what I haue hearde
with myne eares, ſéene with mine eyes, and myne handes haue as it were
handled, I ſée no cauſe why ours &amp; theirs may not iuſtlye
hée coupled together.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:183665:5"/>Theyrs (who knoweth not) tended to the diſhonouring
of God: and to tell thée how many wayes God is diſhonored by ours: I
maye deale with thée, as the ſpyrite of the Lord dealt with the
Prophet <hi>Ezechiel. Sonne of man, beholde the abhominations flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing out of
this filthy fountaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 12.36.</note> 
               <hi>For
euerye ydle worde that man shall ſpeake, shall he geue accoumpt at the daye
of iudgement:</hi> And whether at this playe, there bée any other
almoſt, then ydle wordes vttered, if man wyll not, I call heauen and earth to
wytneſſe. But yet turne thée, and thou ſhalt ſée greater
abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s then this. <hi>That fylthy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication proceede not out of our
mouthes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.29 &amp;. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>but that
whiche is good to the vſe of edifying, that no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes be once named
amongſt vs, as it becommeth Saints: neither fylthines, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foolish
talking, neither ieſting, which are things not comely, but rather geuing of
thanks,</hi> we are by the Apoſtle charged. And whether at theſe meetinges,
theſe thinges bée not commonly vſed: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, wée
finde them forbidden vs by Gods worde: if the offendours wyll not geue glorie
to the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by making confeſſion of their
faultes, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale <pb facs="tcp:183665:5"/> to theyr conſcience, bearing them
wytneſſe, &amp; theyr thoughts accuſing one another, or excuſing. But
yet turne thée, and thou ſhalte ſee greater abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then
theſe. Chriſte condempneth him of adulterye, that looking vppon a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
luſteth after her:<note place="margin">Mat. 5.28</note> but quallyfying the
condempnation of adulterye, becauſe the Lawe of man requyreth ſo precyſe
profe: yet howe the lookes are a prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation therevnto, beléeue the
Wyſe man, and followe his good counſell. <hi>Vſe not the company of a
woman that is a ſinger, and a dauncer, neyther heare her:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>leaſt thou be taken in her
craftineſſe.</hi> Gaze not on a Mayde, that thou fall not by that, that is
precious in her. <hi>The ſonnes of God gazed on the daughters of
men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and ſeeing them fayre, tooke
them wiues of all that they lyked. Therefore the Lorde ſayde: my ſpirite
shall not alwayes ſtriue with man, becauſe hee is but fleshe, his dayes
shall be an hundered and twentye yeares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe of thoſe gazinges what became? Vnlawfull copulations. Of
theſe copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations what? myghty men, and of great renowne, who vſurped
aucthoritie <pb facs="tcp:183665:6"/> ouer others, and degenerated from the ſimplicitie of
theyr forefathers. Of theſe men what? they were myſerably drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the
great deluge. Beholde of this ſmall ſparkle, what raging fyre of
concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence flameth: &amp; ſée of this lytle droppe what a
wonderfull huge water falleth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out the windowes of Heauen, and iſſueth
from the bowels of the earth, to quenche this furious fyre, and that about the
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Maie, when all things floriſh. You O ye ſonnes of men
kéepe company with dauncing Damſels, you gaze vpon them in the moneth
of Maie: beware, you heare out of Gods owne mouth, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll endes enſue.
<hi>A wyſe man wyll not enter the brimmes of daungerous depths, leaſt he
ſoddainly ſlippe ouer headde and eares:</hi> Theſe be the brimmes, come
not nighe them my beloued, (you are not, I feare mée, all
<hi>Ioſephs</hi>) come not nigh them. For though the Rainebow be a certaine
ſigne, that neyther of the Heauen aboue, nor of the earth beneath, the water
wyll deſtroy you: yet wyll there fyre deſcend from the throane of the
almighty <hi>Iehouah</hi> &amp; with brimſtone aſcende out of the fiery
lake,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.8</note> to bée a portion for
them that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede <pb facs="tcp:183665:6"/> to the ende of theſe beginninges.</p>
            <p>But yet turne thée &amp; thou ſhalt ſée grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
abhominations then theſe. Idleneſſe, and Pride, two notable vices
ſpring alſo herehence, as the maſters of many, for the one, who ſee it
by experience in theyr buſineſſe: And for the other theyr gaye geare
aboue their degrée &amp; habilitie, their prowde behauiour and wordes
towards their betters, their rude maners towards their elders, well
wytneſſe and declare. The chyldren of <hi>Iſraelles</hi> dauncing was
done to the golden Calfe, and therefore Idolatry: oures though to tearme it
Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, would ſéeme to ſome, not ſo ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as vntrue, yet
in diuerſe qualities dot hit agrée therewith.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle calleth a couetous perſon an Idolater,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.5.</note> not becauſe he cauſeth an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll to
be made and ſet vp, that bée might adore and worſhip the ſame: but
becauſe he ſerueth Mammon, and who ſo ſerueth Mammon, cannot ſerue
God, and who ſo ſerueth his ryches, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould ſerue him, is an
Idolater. In lyke ſorte, who ſo leaueth the ſeruice of God, to ſerue
his dauncing, &amp; who ſo taketh more delyght in the ſtrength of his
legges, agilitie, and <pb facs="tcp:183665:7"/> nimbleneſſe of his ioyntes, then in the
Goſpel of Chriſt: let the Apoſtles ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce-iudge what he is, and for
my parte, I ſay nothing, but that ſuch abuſe hath béene a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
vs. Notwithſtanding, if a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an once creke againſt theſe workes of
the fleſh, and with as gentle wordes &amp; mylde meanes, as poſſible he
may deuiſe, ſéeke to ſuppreſſe them: Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the very
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens reprehend it with ſharpe tearmes, accoumpting the vſers therof
wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ton, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt, vnchaſte, vnſober, madde, &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy great
reproche: And when the faithful fathers going ſomwhat rounder to work, call
it deuylliſh, with other lyke phraſes, as appeareth in the <hi>Tracte</hi>
following: with cheſe colours, when theſe men blaſe theſe abuſes: if
nowe a dayes, I ſaye, one doo but cypher, he is ſure ſtrayght wayes to be
aſſayed with the Phariſées weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: eyther with ouer curious
reaſons of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deuyce, impertinent and wreſted places of Scriptures,
friuolous and fruitleſſe queſtions: or if theſe preuayle not, then with
iniurious and vniuſt ſclanders: firſt for the firſt ſorte, to touch
onely thoſe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred, or as it is more lykely not at all vttered
in mine Aucthors daies, <pb facs="tcp:183665:7"/> or at leaſt thoſe, which he not vpon
want of knowledge, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope he had wrote inough (as in déede inough
for any reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable man) wyttinglye (as it ſéemeth) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted. To
touch theſe I ſay, their chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt argumentes they would faine fetche
from the examples of the godly men and vertuous women. How ſay ye (ſay
they) by <hi>Iepthes</hi> déere Daughter?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 11.34 Iud. 15.12. Luk. 15.25</note> mett not
ſhée her Father with Tymbrelles &amp; daunces? by the noble
<hi>Iudith?</hi> ledde not ſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daunce her ſelfe? by the pittyfull
father? had not be melodie, and daunceing in his houſe, for ioye his dead
ſonne was reuiued? theſe you cannot deny were vertuous people, and theſe
theyr doings vertuous. But good it is, yea, our bounden duety it is, to follow
the footings of our Forefathers in theyr vertuous actions: and therefore doo we
well in this thing, to imitate their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples which are written for our
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. They are (as the reſt of the Scripture) to this ende lefte in
wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: but beware, leaſt as the ſworde taken by the handle, helpeth, and
by the poynte hurteth: ſo this which ryghtlye receaued, ſerueth for
inſtruction, wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <pb facs="tcp:183665:8"/> receaued, &amp; taken by the wrong end,
ſerue not to deſtruction. In the right imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Auncients,
thrée things are chiefly to be conſidered: fyrſt that we play not
the deceaueable Coyner, who layeth golde vpon copper or braſſe, or ſome
ſuch baſe mettall, to the intent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one might go currant by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes of
the other: ſo that we gylde not, and floriſhe ouer the déedes of the
wicked with the doings of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and then take them both as curra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:
take <hi>Iudas</hi> in with the eleuen Apoſtles, &amp; Sathan with the
ſonnes of God, accept none as our fathers, ſauing thoſe as be the
ſonnes of God. And ſecondarily, in theſe men we muſt not imitate al
thinges, but onelye the good. And thirdly of the good not all too, nor in all
reſpects: but we muſt haue herewith, theſe thrée noates in
conſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deration: vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ſpirit, in what order, to what end they dyd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
For otherwiſe, thoſe that made their doings co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable in the ſight of
the Lorde: if they or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> want in vs, wyl make ours abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. For
the two firſt of the generall diuiſion you haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, good fathers, &amp;
god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Matrones: the laſt you lacke with the thrée braunches, which
turneth the other <pb facs="tcp:183665:8"/> two into bytter wormewood, as by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
together wyll euidently appéere. <hi>Abrahams</hi> offering vp his
déere ſonne &amp; only <hi>Iſaack,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 22.</note> was to him an high praiſe by the mouth
of the Angell, ſaying: <hi>I knowe that thou feareſt God.</hi> The
<hi>Ammonites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 11.7</note> offering vp
their ſonnes and daughters to <hi>Moloche,</hi> is accounted an abhomination:
becauſe the one was of the ſpirit of God, the other of the deuyls, the one
by fayth, the other by infidelytye, the one to Gods glory, the other to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
idolatrous ſeruice of <hi>Moloche.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi>
1.</note> The Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> prayer and inuocation, was ſo wel lyked
of the Lord, that twyſe at his requeſt came fyre from Heauen, and
conſumed the two captains with their fifties:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 9.54</note> 
               <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi>
aſking Chriſt their Maſter, whether they ſhould commaunde that fyre
come downe from heauen to deuowre the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> were ſo much
miſlyked, that they were ſharply reprehended. Beholde héere, how the
facte being all one, the circumſtaunces make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one good, the other ſtarke
naught. The Prophet moued by the ſpyrite of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired this plague to
fall vpon them: the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles moued by an vndiſcreet zeale, and ignoraunt
of what ſpyrite they were, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred <pb facs="tcp:183665:9"/> the lyke. <hi>Ahaziah</hi>
the wicked Apoſtatate, vnder the pretence of holynes ſent to ſlea the
Prophete: the <hi>Samaritanes</hi> denied, but lodging to Chriſt as he
paſſed bye. The Prophete had to deale with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that hauing the worde of
God, forſooke it: the Apoſtles with them that neuer knew the ſame. The
Prophete at the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of almighty God, called downe fire from aboue, to
ſhewe forth his glorye: the Apoſtles by humane affection, were pricked to
reuenge the iniury. The Prophet was ſent to puniſh the infidelity of the
<hi>Iſraelits</hi> (as it may lykewiſe appéere by his kylling the
fowre hundreth &amp; fiftie Prophetes of <hi>Baall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1.
<hi>Kin.</hi> 18.</note> &amp; of the groues fowre hundreth:) the Apoſtles
were ſent to preach the Goſpell, and not to puniſh the contemners
thereof, except extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily: neyther was their Maſters kingdom of this
world, that his ſeruauntes ſhould defende or reuenge his quarrell by any
ſuch meanes.</p>
            <p>Now as we haue labored in laying theſe togeather, (and muche the
more becauſe lyke the Captaine we would beſtowe the greateſt part of our
paines, in batteryng this your principalleſt bulwarke: for this <pb facs="tcp:183665:9"/>
once wonne, that ye haue no hold of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (as trueth you haue not) many
of your ſouldiours wyll ſoone, I doubt not, yéelde) ſo ſet we
theirs and yours, the one by the others. The Daughter of Iudge <hi>Iepthes,
Iudith,</hi> &amp; the good Father, delygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in daunceing, and daunced ſome
them ſelues: you in this poynt doo the lyke. But go further with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this
wide wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of the worlde, vntyll you come, (as <hi>Herculus</hi>
dyd) to the two wayes, the one vertuous, the other voluptuous: and they enter
the waye of vertue, you of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſſe, as apparauntlye declare your
vſuall &amp; wanton wordes, laſciuious ieſtures, and vnchaſt behauiour.
If you can ſay that good men, and godly women, haue vſed this exerciſe,
you haue ſayd, you ſuppoſe ſomething. But alas, this ſome thing is
nothing, by that time you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferre it with thoſe three thinges, that make or
marre all. For though the external actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be in a manner all one, as were
thoſe of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the <hi>Ammonits <hi>Elias,</hi>
               </hi> and the
two diſciples, <hi>Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> yet the cauſe, the maner,
&amp; the end, make as great differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in theſe, as they did in thoſe. The
cauſe of the chaſte Virgin, &amp; worthy wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <pb facs="tcp:183665:10"/> dauncing,
was in token of a ioyfull hart y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord had geuen them or theyr friendes
victory ouer their, and the Lords enemies: your cauſe to ſatiſfye your
vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous pleaſure. Theyr manner was modeſt &amp; moderate to refreſh
their minds &amp; recreate theyr bodies: yours immodeſt, if immodeſtye it
ſelfe be immodeſt, and immoderate, if dauncing all daye long, &amp; parte
of the night bée immoderate: if to toyle &amp; ſweate thereat as if a
man were at mowing: nay, they that ſweat ſo much hereat, neuer ſo much
and ſeldome at all ſweate at worke.</p>
            <p>The cauſe againe of the dauncing and melodye made in the Fathers
houſe, was for ioye his Prodigall chylde was retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the ſinner
repented: and I pray you, which of you euer daunceth for ioye the waſtfull
youth becommeth thryftye, or wicked forſaketh his naughtie wayes? dayly
experience teacheth vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary, that many yong men ſomewhat thriftye,
after they geue them ſelues to daunceing fall to prodigallity? and ſomwhat
vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, become altogeather vicious: or being before but vp to the ſhoe
latchets, nowe are they ſunke vp to the chinne, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <pb facs="tcp:183665:10"/>
great héede, ouer head and eares. The end of theyrs tended to the glory
and honour of almightye God, they ſang the prayſes &amp; myghty works of
the almighty, in their ſober daunces: and at what tyme I beſeech you, at
theſe méetinges ſing you the prayſes, and wonderous workes of God?
Naye, at what tyme is not hée or ſhée laughed to ſcorne, that
ſhoulde ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue them ſelues? ſo farre are you from theyr godly
paſtimes. Wherefore for ſhame ceaſe to cyte this that makes ſo much
againſt you, and as pure whyte ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth your fowle and ſteyned
blacke: and if you haue any other &amp; better, bring them forth. Better we
haue not, neyther can we (for where ſo good maye be found, as in holy
Scripture) but other we haue, whereby we wyll no more contende, that this
laſciuious leaping of oures is ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable at all tymes, but onely at
<hi>VVhyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſontide,</hi> and that for thrée cauſes: that we may vſe
reioyſing in remembraunce the holy Ghoſte deſcended to illuminate the
hartes &amp; mindes of men: that the Church might be the better by this meanes
main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned: and that the youth might eſchew ydle thoughtes, which by
ſytting ſtyll and <pb facs="tcp:183665:11"/> doing nothing would ſoone
poſſeſſe theyr heads, and thereout would quickly flame euyll
deedes.</p>
            <p>The Kings of <hi>Iuda</hi> that walked in the wayes of their
father <hi>Dauid,</hi> pulled down all Monuments of Idolatry, ſauing that the
high places ſtoode ſtyll: God forbyd my beloued Brethren, that you
ſhoulde roote out other oportunities of daunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and diſallowe all other
tymes and places, and yet ſuffer this high place to continew. If it be euil,
or euilly vſed, then playe the parte of good King <hi>Joſias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> King. 23</note> downe with al, yea, euen with this
high place too, wherein and in which tyme this abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is at the
higheſt. If it be good, yet let vs not doo this good, that the euylles
already rehearſed maye followe.<note place="margin">Roma. 3.8.</note> But
theſe general examples and exhortations becauſe they poynt not (as they
thinke) dyrectly at them: I wyll (God wylling) therefore enter into particular
examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and anſwer them ſeuerally by them ſelues.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt for reioyſing at the feaſt of <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſt,</hi>
that the comforter came downe in the viſible forme of fierie clouen tongues:
what other ioye is better &amp; méeter, then <pb facs="tcp:183665:11"/> the comforter
him ſelfe requireth? and what is that ioy be ſheweth by the mouth of his
ſeruaunt <hi>Iaemes,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.13.</note> is
any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you afflycted? let him praye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is any mery? let him ſinge. And
what he ſhould ſinge, he declareth by the penne of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy writer the
Apoſtel <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying:<note place="margin">Eph. 5.19.</note>
               <hi>Speak vnto your ſelues in Himmes and Pſalmes and ſpirituall ſonges,
ſinging and making melodie, to the Lord in your hartes.</hi> More ouer if we
wyll reioyce for the comming of the holy ſpirit, what other reioyſing is
ſo good and méete for a Chriſtian, as that Primatiue and firſt
reioyſing at his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſcenſion? what decenter order, what
goodlier and godlier exerciſe, then the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and the religious
multitude ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together out of many Nations to ſerue the Lorde, kept at
that feaſte of Whitſontide? We reioyce (we ſaye) and we gather our
ſelues together out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny townes: but in what order reioyce we and to what
ende flocke we ſo faſt togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? in no ſuch order, to no ſuch ende
(the Lord knoweth) as thoſe Apoſtles and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Diſciples bid. The
Apoſtls when the day of Penticoſt was come,<note place="margin">Actes.
2.</note> were all with one accorde in one place, and were <pb facs="tcp:183665:12"/> filled
with the holy Ghoſt: the people wondered at the wonderfull working of the
ſpirit: the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> painefully preched the word of God, the
people heard him and conſtantly continued in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples doctrine. The
Apoſtles miniſtred the ſupper of the Lord (ſo much ſignifieth to vs
the breaking of bread) the people accompanied them in that godly felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.
And to be briefe both Apoſtles and people perſeuered together in prayer, in
gladnes, and in ſinglenes of heart. Marke this manner of gladnes and tell mee
whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ours in reſpect hereof be not méere madneſſe. We are
together but full farre from one accord, as our dayly debates de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare: we are
filled, not with the holye Ghoſt, but with ſtrong ale: we come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
from diuerſe places, to ſerue the Lorde? no, to ſerue our voluptuous
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. We preach, but what preach we? y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel of Chriſt, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
ſinnes &amp; abhomina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mich.</hi>
2.11</note> as <hi>Peter</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did? nothing leſſe: but we prophecy
&amp; preach of pleſure, of ſtrong drinke, of wine, and then are we
Prophets for this people, then are we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted honeſt men. We communicate,
and what doo we cumunicat, the ſupper of <pb facs="tcp:183665:12"/> the Lord? nay that
were to ſadde a matter for ſo mery a time, and yt woulde let much good
ſport. But we communicate many idle words, many vnſeamely ieſts, I wyll
ſay no more for ſparing you. So that this vnchriſtian behauiour of ours
ſheweth vs to celebrate the feaſt rather of <hi>Bacchus</hi> then of the
holy Ghoſt. Seconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily for the maintaynance of the Church, there are other
and better meanes then this, as you your ſelues right wel knowe. Oh, but you
muſt conſider, (wyll they ſay) that they would not giue at all were it
not to this ende. Nowe truely, better well ſpared then ſo euill ſpent:
and as for the reperations of the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Kin.
12.4</note> King <hi>Ioas</hi> ſheweth a ſeeme lyer order, &amp; though
this lawe bee aboliſhed, yet haue our owne lawes prouided the lyke: vſe
that a Gods name, and as for this vnlawful &amp; wicked way, let it ſerue the
ſinagogue of Satan, for the Temple of the Lorde was at no time by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly,
by theſe vngodly wayes vpholden. Thirdelye for baniſhing idle thoughts out
of your childrens &amp; ſeruants minds, who worketh this way, drowneth a
fiſh in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water, &amp; putteth out alamp with oyle, as playnely appeareth
both by that <pb facs="tcp:183665:13"/> which goeth, before and that which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, after.
Theſe are one ſorte of the Weapons, the other (as I ſayd) are
ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, wherewith they intreat them which reprehend theſe abuſes,
much after the manner the <hi>Lybertines</hi> intreated <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen.</hi> When
<hi>Stephen</hi> repleate with the holy Ghoſt diſputed againſt certaine
<hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines Cirenians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 6.</note>
               <hi>Alexandrians,</hi> and <hi>Cilicians,</hi> they not able to reſiſt the
wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and the ſpirit by whiche be ſpake, ſuborned falſe witnes,
who teſtified they hard him ſays that Ieſus of Nazareth ſhoulde
deſtroye that place and chaunge the ordinances which <hi>Moyſes</hi> gaue
them? and thus moued they the Scribes, the elders<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the people
againſt him. In like ſort theſe looſe Libertines reaſon with thoſe
arguments and auctthorities before mentioned and when they bée not able
to withſtand the word of God and ſpirit that ſpeaketh in his true
miniſters, then ſeke they out and ſet vp falſe wytneſſe, who
ſlaunderouſly report that we goo about to deſtroye all, to chaunge the
auncient ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances <hi>Moyſes</hi> gaue them, to alter al olde cuſtomes
their forefathers leaft them, to put down al honeſt and laudable paſtime, 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:13"/> to ende all friendly and neyghbourlye méetinges and mery
makinges, to cut of good occaſions of loue among men and charity towards the
poore: and thus ſtirre they the Scribes, the Elders and the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple
againſte vs well, for them I ſaye no more, but remember the commandement of
almighty God, thou ſhalt not beare falſe wytneſſe againſt thy
neighbour. For you, ye Magiſtrats, Miniſters and people I exhort in the
Lord, that ye be not ouer creduloſe in theſe matters, leaſte in quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<hi>Barrabas</hi> you condemne Chriſt, and in letting goo theſe
ſlaunderous witneſſe, ye puniſhe innocent <hi>Stephen.</hi> Suffer
mée a whyle to pleade our owne cauſe in your preſence, and you
ſhal plainely perceaue, howe theſe vniuſt accuſations they laye to our
charge, may iuſtly be turned vpon them: For firſt they by their
abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, endeuour to deſtroy all, to breake the ordinaunces of
<hi>Moiſes</hi> and olde cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes of the primatiue Church, and pureſt
tymes. There are manye thinges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this lewde and licentious
exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe: flat againſt <hi>Moiſes</hi> mind, as his dede declared:
againſt his ordinaunces, as his lawes (who liſt to conferre them with
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiels <pb facs="tcp:183665:14"/> for ſhewed ſight) make manifeſt. By their
voluptuous ſport they put downe all honeſt lawefull and lawdable paſtime,
namely ſhuting, and eſpecially at that ſeaſon, when for the number and
length of the holy dayes they are at moſt leaſure, and for the
freſhneſſe of the ayer and ſwéetneſſe of the fieldes, they
may take moſt delight. The Prince comands it, the wiſe commends it, the
warre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels it, and yet rude royat ſhall preuayle againſt them all. By
their vnciuell and vnmannerly vſage, friendly and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly company and
communication is quite diſſolued and broken of. The caters cheife care,
muſt it not be for the youth, howſoeuer the age? for the ſeruaunt
how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the maſter? for the ſonne, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the father fareth. The
beſt and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt roomes, be they not kept for the young men and maidens,
whereſoeuer the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſubſtantial, and honeſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Parriſh
ſit? nay if they be ſate, be their meetinges neuer ſo neighbourly, their
communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neuer ſo friendly, their matters ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo weighty, muſt
they not away, my Lorde commeth? But this is but once a yeare, and in ieſt
manye wyll aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, <pb facs="tcp:183665:14"/> no more is this oportunitie of this
neighbourly méeting, but once a yeare, and therefore to be preferred
this once: and this ieſt, turneth commonly to ſuch earneſt all the yeare
after, that Gods commaundement is broken, Honour thy Father and Mother:<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.5.</note> the Apoſtles precept neglected, Seruants obey
your maſters. By their brawles and ſometyme blowes betwéene company
and company, the linkes of loue are often ſeuered a ſunder. By their
ouermuch eating and drinking, charity to the poore waxeth colde. For doo they
not ride from towne to towne, goe from village to village gulling in ſtrong
drinke, and glutting in good meate, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture being before ſufficed, that might
be better beſtowed vpon the neceſſity of the ſaynctes? I wyll ſay
nothing here of the gluttony and drunkennes comitted ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the practiſe
and ſport that I haue ſéene to make a man ouercome with nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ale:
but what if I (to ſpare you) ſaye nothing, neuertheleſſe the Apoſtle
ſayth, <hi>That drounkardes ſhall not inherit the kingdome of
heauen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10 <hi>Aba.</hi> 2.15</note>
And the Prophet cryeth, <hi>VVoe vnto him that geueth his neyghbour drinke to
make him drunken.</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:183665:15"/> Farre better were it (beloued brethren)
that this Dauncing the cauſe of this great and gréeuous ſinne (for
take away Daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and down fales al) ſhould be vtterly aboliſhed, then
that on ſoule ſhould periſh, or one of theſe woes ſhould light vpon
vs. It is a ſore and terrible thing to fall into the hands of the Lord.
Tuſhe wyl ſume ſay, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo delighteth in drinking &amp; daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing if
he haue it not here, wil haue in it a nother place &amp; wil do it though this
were not: &amp; therfore it is better to let them haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at home, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
ſhould raung about. As though other places bée not, or ought not to be
in this good order? or as though y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhouldeſt noriſh naughtineſſe,
becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do ſo? or as though thy fatherly fear, and maſterly
aucthority were not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſuppreſſe this ſinne &amp;
wickedneſſe? In excuſing this one fault, thou makeſt thrée.
Firſt thou apeacheſt other places of like lewdnes: next that thou maiſt
follow their examples: and laſt of all, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſelfe wanteſt wiſdom
&amp; diſcretion to rule thine vnruly familie. If other Towns were ſo
vntoward as thou makeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that thou ſhouldeſt
aſſociate them? If other youth be ſo euyll bent, muſt thine 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:15"/> néedes acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany them? God forbyd. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> that
good father, &amp; godly maſter, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all other Nations round about him, were
wholy geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all maner of abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, kept his houſehold in ſuch feare
of God, &amp; ſo well inſtructed them in his word, that they wyllingly
receaued Circumciſion at his handes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi>
17.23</note> If <hi>Abraham</hi> had ſayd as you ſaye, I were beſt to
ſuffer my familie to run royat at home, for otherwiſe they wil in other
places round about mée: would they, thinke you, without reſiſtance
haue ſuffered the impreſſion of this couenaunt, being ſo grieuous a
ſore, that the <hi>Seheehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> ſicke therewith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.25</note> were a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ouercome by two
perſons, <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui?</hi> Neyther the multitud of many
cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries could moue <hi>Abraham</hi> to let loſe the reynes to his tender
youth: nor the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſore againe of Circumciſion, coulde cauſe his
houſeholde to withſtand his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: You haue not (God be prayſed) ſo
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (though too many) againſt you:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi>
16.10</note> neyther would I wiſh you, nor is it my minde to lay this, or the
lyke yoake on your necks, which neyther our fathers, nor wée were able,
to bear as ſome complain, ſaying, we would haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> liue like Saints, (as
who <pb facs="tcp:183665:16"/> woulde ſaye that were euill (which is to ſtrayght for
them) but we deſire to lay on your ſhoulders the yoke of Chriſt and his
light burthen. And if it fall out that all towneſhips round about you, or, if
al the towne which you inhabite maintain this miſdemeanure, yet would I
counſell a Chriſtian to ſay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Captaine <hi>Ioſua, Choſe you whether
you vvyl ſerue God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſu.</hi> 24.15</note>
               <hi>as your vain pleſure, I &amp; mine houſe vvil ſerue the Lord.</hi>
This accompt if euery man would make as he ought, this diſorder would be
quickly redreſſed. Thus haue you heard howe they are fallen into the pyttes
they digged for others and now a word or two howe <hi>Stephen</hi> is not onely
cleare of theſe ſlaunderous accuſations, but alſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
deſireth that whereof they accuſe him. They accuſe him to ſaye that
Ieſus of Nazareth (it can be none other ſo long as hee preacheth none but
Ieſus) woulde chaunge the ordinaunces <hi>Moyſes</hi> gaue them, the
auncient cuſtomes their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers leaft them, where he teacheth that
Chriſt came not to deſtroye the lawes of <hi>Moyſes</hi> but to fulfill
them. They from this generall and falſe poſition, diſcend to as falſe
particulars, bringing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne <pb facs="tcp:183665:16"/> late and newe orders of merye
makings and friendly méetings of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and of reléeuing
the néedye, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them olde orders if they can cal them ſo, or if
they be out of their remembrance, or if they haue bene vſed an age or two
before them: whereas hée endeuoureth to aboliſh the ſtraunge
innouations &amp; newe fangles, and to call them backe to the old cuſtumes
and auncient orders in déede.</p>
            <p>In the primatiue Church the faithfull made feaſts amonge them
ſelues,<note place="margin">Iude ver. <hi>12</hi>
               </note> partly to proteſt
their brotherly loue, and partly to reléeue the poore people. The
auncient Father <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">Chriſo.
vpon Gen. ho. 10.</note> Let one of you take the holye booke, and let hym call
hys neyghbours aboute him, and by the heauenlye wordes let him water and
refreſhe boeth their mindes, and alſo his owne, that by this meanes we maye
bee able to eſcape the Deceiptes of the Deuyll. You that ſticke ſo faſt
to olde cuſtoms and haue alwayes in your mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes let vs kéepe olde
cuſtomes, leaue thoſe your newe and naught, and kepe theſe oulde and good
couſtomes: or at the leaſte chaunge youre common ſong, and ſing another
whyle: Ours be of <pb facs="tcp:183665:17"/> late ſince iniquity hath got the vpperha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
&amp; yours of olde in the primitiue Church, &amp; time of the auncient
Fathers. But for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as neyther the good counſell of this auncient
Father, nor the ſhyning mirror of this primitiue Church, ſo much moue many
as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of the Prince and her Magiſtrates, I wyll therefore
thereof ſpeake ſomewhat, that I may win ſome. The Quéenes
Maieſtie in the twentie article of her <hi>Iniunctions,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth
that her faythfull and louing ſubiects celebrate, &amp; keepe their holy
daies according to Gods holy wyll &amp; pleaſure: that is, in hearing the
word of God read &amp; taught: in priuate &amp; publique prayers: in
acknowledging their offences to God, and amendment of the ſame: in
reconcilyng themſelues charitably to their neighbors, where diſpleaſure
hath bene: in often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing the Communion, in viſiting the poore and
ſicke, in vſing al ſoberneſſe and godly conuerſation. Hitherto the
wordes of the <hi>Iniunction:</hi> Wherein albeit daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing be not named, &amp;
namely forbydden, yet is it as ſtraightly denied, as if it were
expreſſed. For in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunding godlines to be vſed, wickednes is denied:
&amp; whoſoeuer accompliſheth her Maieſties moſt godlye <pb facs="tcp:183665:17"/>
minde in theſe pointes, ſhal haue (I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant him) litle leaſure and
leſſe pleaſure to daunce and dallye: and whereſoeuer theſe godlye
exerciſes be put in practiſe, dauncinge <hi>Dagon</hi> will downe before
the arke, the ſeuereſt <hi>Saul</hi> that ſeeketh to per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecute ſuche
as ſpeake againſt theſe abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, will him ſelfe fall to prophecyeing?
The ſturdieſt ſoldier that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to take <hi>Chriſt</hi> will
ſtagger, and fall flatte to the ground, as many happy places and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
perſons in theſe daies well wittneſſe and declare: where &amp; among
whom the arke (the bible co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teining the teſtimonies not of <hi>Arons</hi>
rodde &amp; the potte of <hi>Manna</hi> alone, but manye more myracles,
togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the two tables) is ſo ſet vp, that the idoll of dauncing
breakes his necke. The ſpirite of God ſo mightely worketh, that diuerſe,
of perſecutours, are become defendors of Gods people: the wordes of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo effectually pronounced, that ſuch as will not yeilde,
they ſtrike downe to the earth. This is the Lords doeyng and it is marueilous
in our eyes.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtandinge ſome much like <hi>Thomas Didimus,</hi> will
not beléeue that this article of the Princes toucheth this <pb facs="tcp:183665:18"/>
diſorder, becauſe they here not dauncing expreſſly named. Theſe men I
referre to Maiſter <hi>Godwinnes. 47.</hi> article, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the title of
Church wardens &amp; ſworne men: who are ſworne to ſée the ſame
ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolliſhed, God geue them his grace to diſcharge theyr othe: Whiche that
they might the rather doe, this beſides diuerſe other, was one cauſe I
tooke this taſke in hande. Others were to moue the Magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates by the
example of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 32.19</note> to ſtoppe
this outragious paſtimes, to ſtirre my bretheren, whome the Lord hath
appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted watchmen ouer his flockes, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe them of theyr wicked
wayes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 3.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 33.6</note>
leaſt theyr bloude be not one day required at theyr hands: and for parte of
diſcharge of this my charge amonge the reſt, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto the people
theſe abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: that the mouthes of the malitious maye be muſled,
readinge and iudginge (by this meanes) at theyr leaſure, the doctrine I haue
taughte them, to be no olde wiues tale, nor corrupt cuſtome, nor vayne
inuention of man, as theires is, but the worde of the Lorde, rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge theyr
ſinnes, whereof I and ſuche as I am: vppon payne (you hearde euen 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:18"/> nowe of euerlaſting death, are ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye charged to
admoniſhe you, and that the hartes of the honeſt, whoe more for wante the
watchman warneth them not theſe offences,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cro.</hi>
29.36. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30.14.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 31.1 <hi>Ezra.</hi> 8.15</note>
then for obſtinate and wilfull frowardneſſe (for truelye to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte as I
fynd, the people are often rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to doe theyr duetie to the Lord, then the
Prieſtes and Leuites, and willinger to obey his wil then the ſonnes of
<hi>Leuie</hi>) that theſe mens hartes (I ſaye) ſeinge now how they haue
heretofore of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce in the word of God, and not thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to be ſo
euill as they here in mine Authors tracte ſée it is, done amyſſe
may be ſo inwardly touched y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may ſaye: Men and bretheren, what
ſhall we doe?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.27.</note> And becauſe no
Prophet is eſtéemed in his owne countrie, I haue thought it good to
take a worthye Prophet of another countrye, that thou mighteſt not diſdaine
to bee taughte, at his handes, whoe once taught the learned Diuines in Oxforde:
and that thou mighteſte not refuſe to be tolde thy faulte, whether it be of
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce or ignoraunce (for if of ignoraunce,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi>
4.</note> yet a faulte, as ſhewethe the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions offered therefore) by
ſuche a <pb facs="tcp:183665:19"/> one as rebuked euen Kings for <hi>Chriſtes</hi>
ſake, and Princes by the waighty words of his wrytinges. Finallye that thou
mighteſt in litle tyme reade in thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue: and for a litle monye
buye not ſo much a litle booke according to the quantitye, as a whole
librarye of bookes according to the quallitye. For by the wonderfull paines of
this ſedulous Bée, haſt thou here the honnie of moſte artes
concerning this matter. Art thou a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, and of the diuines a fauourer of
the truth? Here haſt thou examples of the ſcripture, generall councelles
and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers: or a fauourer of the Pope? here haſt thou popes &amp;
popiſh ſcholemen. Art thou a lawier, and of the lawiers a ciuilian? here is
ciuill lawe: or a Canno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt? here are Cannons, diſtinctions, and
decrées: Studieſt thou Philoſophy? here Philoſophers ſpeake
theyr mindes: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt thou in Oratorye? here Orators vtter their eloquent
ſentences: or in Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriography? here Hiſtories ar declared: dwelleſt
thou in the country, and deſireſt to haue theyr obiections anſwered? here
are they anſwered. Briefly he is of a very ſtraunge decrée and
condition of lyfe <pb facs="tcp:183665:19"/> that may not in this ſmale tract of
Maiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Martyres,</hi> in his owne profeſſyon be brought familyarly
from this vice to the better knowledge of Chriſt, as were the Aſtronomers
by a ſtar, and <hi>Peter</hi> the fiſherman by a myraculous draughte of
fiſhe: which God to the glory of his name graunt. <hi>So be it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:20"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A briefe Tracte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>cerning Dauncing collected</hi>
out of Maiſter Doctour Peter <hi>Martyr,</hi> by <hi>Maiſter</hi>
Maſſonius.</head>
            <p>DAuncing, as <hi>Plato</hi> ſaieth, is ſayde to be of
reioycing: for that it is a certain teſtimonie of ioy and gladneſſe. And
<hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> interpreting that verſe of <hi>Virgill. <hi>Omnis qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
chorus et ſocij co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitantur oua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whom all the companye of daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and fellowes followed
reioycinge: ſaieth the ſame to be a ſinginge and leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of them that
are of one age. But from whence this ſhoulde take it begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge, there are
diuerſe opinions.</p>
            <p>Some ſuppoſe, that men beholdinge the motions of the fixed and
wanderinge Starres, inuented this, therby to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that variety of the
motion. Others thinke that it rather ſprange fyrſte of Religion, becauſe
amonge the auncient <hi>Ethnickes,</hi> no ſacred thinges were wel nie donne
without dauncinge.</p>
            <p>For they leade theyr daunces from the leafte to the right ſide
of the Aulter, to ſhewe the turninge of Heauen from <pb facs="tcp:183665:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:183665:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:183665:22"/> the Eaſte to the
Weaſt, then returned they from the right ſide to the leafte, to ſignify
the courſe of the moueable and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moueable ſtarres: which thinge
perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture <hi>Virgill</hi> meant, when be ſayde: 
<q>Inſtaurant<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> choros mixti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> altaria circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</q> They
begine to daunce afreſh one with another round about the aulters.<note place="margin">salij vvere prieſtes of Mars in Rome, vvh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ich daunced about the
ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie vvith tar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatts called Ancilia.</note> Alſo <hi>Salij</hi> the
prieſtes of <hi>Mars</hi> among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines were had in great eſtimation.
And there be that referre the originall hereof to <hi>Hiero Siculus</hi> the
tyraunt: who, as they reporte, to eſtabliſh his tyranny, forbad the people
mutuall communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. By meanes wherof it came to paſſe, that the men of
<hi>Sicilia</hi> beganne to exprſſe theyr mindes and thoughtes by beckes
&amp; geſtures of the bodie: which afterwards grew to an vſe and cuſtom.
But whether this be ſo or noe, daunces in the olde time were not
enſtraunged from religion: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit afterwardes they were applyed to publique
and common reioyſing: Beſides theſe, there was another kinde exerciſed
by younge men in Martiall affayres.</p>
            <p>For aſmuch as they were commaunded to leappe and make muche
geſture and ſignes of mirth in theyr Harnes, to thend <pb facs="tcp:183665:22"/> they
might be readier and apter for bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, when the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common welath
ſo required.<note place="margin">Pyrricha a certain form of dauncing vſed of
ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diors, and iuented by Pyrehus.</note> This manner of daunſinge was
called <hi>Pyrrhicha,</hi> and becauſe it was vſed in armour, armed, hereof
mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made in the ciuill lawes, (that is to ſaye) in the digeſt of
puniſhmentes, F. <hi>de poenis:</hi> L. <hi>ad damnum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſometyme younge men, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they treſpaſſed, were not
foorthwith adiudged to dye, but either to hunte in the theater, or to daunce in
theyr armour: and they were called <hi>Pyrrhicharij.</hi> Another kinde alſo
there was, which was appointed for pleaſure, onely and laſciuiouſnes,
called of the <hi>Gretians</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a rude ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and
ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſe kinde of dauncing in comaedies.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer of them that expreſſed by the geſtures of theyr
bodies the meaning of theyr mindes: wryteth <hi>Lucianus</hi> in his Treaty of
dauncing, &amp; likwiſe <hi>Athenaeus:</hi> Which came to that paſſe at
length, that <hi>Demetrius Cynicus</hi> in deriſion called thys counterfeit
dauncing a vaine thing and nothing worth. Whereupon a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy dauncer, whoe
then was had in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at <hi>Rome,</hi> deſyred him that he would but one
onelye tyme beholde him, and then that hee woulde iudge and reporte 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:23"/> whatſoeuer pleaſed him. He came to the Theater, the
counterfeite beganne by his geſtures to expreſſe the common fable of
<hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> taken in adulterye. Wherein in ſuche
ſorte, he ſhewed the Sonne diſcloſinge, <hi>Vulcan</hi> knittinge
nettes, <hi>Venus</hi> all aſhamed, and <hi>Mars</hi> humbly intreating, in
ſo much as <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius</hi> aſtonied cryed out. I not onely
ſée, O man, the thinges thou doeſt, but alſo here them. For by thy
handes thou ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt to ſpeake vnto me. At the ſame tyme, as it
happened, there repayred to <hi>Rome,</hi> the kinge of <hi>Pontus:</hi> Who
when he had ſéene this dauncer play his geſturs in the Theater,
afterwardes willed to demaund of <hi>Nero,</hi> the thinge he chieflye wiſhed
to be beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, he aſked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> geſturer: wherat <hi>Nero</hi>
maruelyng, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he might haue requeſted other things of much more
valew, inquired the cauſe of his requeſt. He made anſwere, becauſe I
haue many nations vnder my ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whom without an interpreter, I
ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vnderſtande, and eftſoomes it falleth out, that interproters
declare not faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully enough my wordes vnto them, nor agayne theyrs vnto me:
But this fellow <pb facs="tcp:183665:23"/> by hys geſtures wyll declare all thynges
moſte faythfullye. <hi>Plato</hi> in his thyrde booke of lawes, maketh two
manners of daunces, the one warlike, whiche aboue we named <hi>Pyrrhicha,</hi>
the other peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wkich he termeth placable.</p>
            <p>The vncleane and filthy kinde I omit to ſpeake of, becauſe it
is manefeſtſlye condemned by the lawes. The exerciſe in harnes and that
which was ſhewed by ſignes, maye ſerue to ſome vſe in the common
wealth: but to our purpoſe they perteine not. Wherefore of the pecea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and
placable ſorte, ſhall ſomewhat be ſayde in thys place, howe farre
foorth it maye be lawefull, when for reioycinge ſake it is vſed.</p>
            <p>This kinde of exerciſe ſéemeth to me of it owne nature
neither vitiouſe nor to be prohibited, for aſmuche as agillitye and
nimbleneſſe of the boddye, is the gifte of God: and if there be added
ſome arte, that the boddye be mooued with decencye, iuſt pace, &amp;
comlines, I ſee not why it ought to be reprehended, ſo it be done in due
ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, moderatly and without offence. For as it is lawfull to ſinge,
&amp; vſe ſinginge to giue thanks to god, &amp; celebrat his praiſes: 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:24"/> So likewiſe moderate dauncing to teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify our ioy and
gladneſſe.<note place="margin">2. Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 6.14</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi>
doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe daunced openly before the Arke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 18.6</note>The maidens renowmed his
victorye ouer <hi>Goliah</hi> with dauncing and ſinging. <hi>Miriam
Moſes</hi> ſiſter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 15.20</note> when
<hi>Pharo</hi> was layde a longe and ſlaine, daunced with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther women, and
ſange a ſonge of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph and victorie. Wherefore ſith holy men and
chaſt wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue vſed daunces, we can not ſaye they are faultye of theyr
owne nature: but as they are nowe a dayes donne, that men ſhould daunce
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geyther with women, they be vntollera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble: For that they are the nutrimentes
and prouocations of laſciuiouſneſſe and voluptuous pleaſures.
<hi>Mirriam Moſes</hi> ſiſter traced not with younge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte
with women: neither <hi>Dauid</hi> with women, nor the maidens who honoured his
conqueſt, with yonge men but by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues. Now they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with all theyr
mind and might loue God, it is not enough for them to obſerue his
commaundements, vnleſſe they cutte of alſo all occaſiones, whereby
theyr obſeruations maye be impayred. But our daunces are moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
occaſions of tranſgreſſing the diuine <pb facs="tcp:183665:24"/> lawe: ſnares they
are and ſtumblinge blockes, not to the doers alone but to the beholders
alſo: For they ſtirre and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the hart of men, wicked enoughe
otherwiſe from it verye beginning: and what with much a doe and induſtry,
is to be repreſſed, that the flickeringe intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of theſe light
leapinges rayſe &amp; ſtyrre vp. Verely if a man would take counſell
either of him ſelfe, or of expery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or of reaſon, he ſhall finde the
luſter of the minde not a litle to be kindled, and ſet on fyre by theſe
ſightes: and he ſhall perceiue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with waue of theyr goodnes, and women
with eclyppes of theyr chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie returne home. Furthermore, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles are
rather to be taken héede of then nouriſhed: For as <hi>Salamon</hi>
ſaith, <hi>VVho loueth perill shall fall thereinto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome man will obiecte, that daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinges ſo muche indammage
manners, and kindle luſte, commethe to paſſe by raſhneſſe and by
accedentarye meanes: and iudgement ought not of euery thing to be geuen,
accordinge to thoſe thinges whiche come by chaunce, but according to theſe
thinges that are here in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Some are founde ſo chaſte 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:25"/> and pure, that they can with a chaſte and pure minde
ſée theſe ſightes. I graunt it may ſometyme ſo fall out, but
take thys with you, all accedentes not to be of the ſame condition.</p>
            <p>Some there are which verie ſeldome happen, ſome eyther way,
which of their nature maye be aſwell preſent at anye thinge, as abſent:
and ſoome whiche for the moſt parte are wont to fall out: theſe laſt in
each thinge ought to be moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently conſidered and regarded: neither
muſt we reſpecte what maye, but what was wont to be done.
<hi>Ariſtippus</hi> daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in purple, and therof accuſed, excuſed
himſelfe that therby he waxed neuer the worſe, and that he could euen in
that ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenes and delicacye retaine a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers minde. But ſuch
ſayinges are not to be herkened vnto: becauſe as <hi>Demoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes</hi>
ſaieth, and is cited of the Lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers, we muſt not concider what any man
doth now and then, but what is accoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be done for the moſt parte.
Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine a man to be ſo chaſte, that he maye not be moued with theſe
allurementes, yet in the meane whyle howe are the people prouided for, and the
multitude <pb facs="tcp:183665:25"/> ſéene vnto? For the integrety &amp;
vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome one or other, ſhall we ſuffer all the reſt to
remaine in danger? But ſo, wil ſome man mutter, take a waye Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and
Sacraments, for many heare ſomtime the word of God to their own
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demnation, and to their owne condemnae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion many eat &amp; drink the holy
Miſteries.</p>
            <p>Here is it neceſſary to be knowne that ſome thinges make for
mens ſaluation, and are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by the word of God, which by no meanes
ought to be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Some thinges againe are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, which if we
ſée them tende to hurte, are not tollerable. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Sermons &amp;
Sacraments, we haue the lawe of God that we ſhoulde heare and receiue them:
touching dauncing there is nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded: Wherefore theſe are not to be
compared togither. But by this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (ſaye diuerſe) are manye honeſt
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages made. It maye be ſo otherwhile, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding for my parte, it
could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſinke into mine heade, that I would wiſh Matrimonies to be by
theſe means contracted, wherin the nimbeneſſe onely &amp; bewtie of the
body are reſpected. Ther are other meanes far honeſter, let vs vſe 
<pb facs="tcp:183665:26"/> them, and as for theſe ſcarce honeſt and chaſt, let vs
leaue them. Weigh we with our ſelues, that although ſomtime honeſt
mariages be gotten by dauncinge: yet a great deale oftener adultrye and
whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome are wonnte to enſue of theſe ſights.</p>
            <p>We ſhould followe the footings of our godly Fatherrs, who now
and then vſed dauncinge, yet chaſte and moderate, the men by them ſelues,
and the women by theyr ſelues: By theſe daunces teſtified they the myrthe
of their mindes, ſangs they prayſes to God, gaue they thankes vnto him for
ſome ſingular benefite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued at his handes. And as for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
daunces of men and women togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we reade them not in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.
But our men wil ſaye, who would daunce after this ſorte? Theſe thinges
while they vtter, they bewray the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues what they ſéeke for in this
paſtime.</p>
            <p>Hyther flocke the effects of dauncinge recorded in
<hi>Mathew,</hi> how the daughter of <hi>Herodias</hi> ſkipped in the kinges
feaſt, the king toke pleaſur in her, whome without ſhame he could not
ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly gaze vppon: for it was a moſt euident token of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forbide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marriage
&amp; whoredome: for <hi>Herod</hi> had <pb facs="tcp:183665:26"/> taken vnto him the wyfe
of his brother, and mother of this damſell: of that daunce it followed that
<hi>Iohn</hi> was bee headded. Many are miſgréeued with vs, that
wée cye out vppon daunces, as vppon things: euill of their nature and
prohibited. We again make aunſwere, that things ought not alwayes to be
meaſured, by their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the diſpoſition and abuſe of our
fleſhe: wine, we cannot, denye, of it ſelfe is good: yet is it not
adminiſtred to the ſick of the Feuer: not in that it is euil, but in that
it agreeth not with the bodye ſo affected. In <hi>Exodus</hi> when the people
made to themſelues a golden calfe, which they might worſhippe, they ſate
downe, they eate, they drancke, and they roſe vp to play: In which place to
play ſéemeth to be nothing elſe then to daunce. But that I may not
ſéeme ſingular and alone man in theſe my ſayinges and cenſure,
I wyll annexe certaine teſtimonies of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
in the ſixt Chapter of his booke againſt <hi>Petilian,</hi> ſayth:
Byſhops were euermore wont to puniſh vaine and laſcinious daunces: but
now a daies, there be many Biſhops not only preſent at the daunces, but
dauncers themſelues with <pb facs="tcp:183665:27"/> women: ſo farre are they from
correcting this vice. The ſame <hi>Auguſtine</hi> whyle he expoundeth
thoſe words of the <hi>.32.</hi> Pſalme Vppon an inſtrument of tenne
ſtringes will I ſinge vnto thee: thoſe ten ſtringes he maketh the tenne
commaundements, and when he had ſayde ſome what vppon euery one of them, at
the laſt he commeth to the Saboth: of which it is written, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that
thou kéepe holy the Saboth day: I ſay not (ſayth he) that thou
ſhouldeſt be ſo drowned in delicacie, as the <hi>Iewes</hi> are
accuſtomed: for better it is all day to dig, then to daunce on the Saboth,
<hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> in <hi>.56.</hi> Homely vppon <hi>Genneſes,</hi>
intreating of <hi>Iacobs</hi> Mariage, Mariage (quoth he) haue ye hearde, but
no daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, which there he calleth <hi>Diabolicall:</hi> and many more
matters hath hée in the ſame place, which make for vs. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge all
the reſt be wryteth howe by dauncing, the Bride and Bridegrume are corrupted,
and the whole family defiled. Againe in his <hi>.48. Hom.</hi> Thou
ſéeſt, ſayth he, Mariages but daunces thou ſéeſt not.
For at that time they were nothing ſo wanton as they are in theſe dayes.
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other thinges hath he in the <hi>.14.</hi> of <hi>Matthew,</hi> wher
reciting <hi>Herodius</hi> daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <pb facs="tcp:183665:27"/> to the people, among the
reſt, he ſaith now a daies Chriſtians deliuer not halfe their kingdome
nor another mans head, but their own ſoule into diſtruction. And he addeth,
where this laſciuious dauncing is ſet vp, there daunceth the Deuill
toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them. In the counſell of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi> we finde written,
that it is not conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for Chriſtian men to daunce at Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
dine and ſuppe diſcréetly and moderatelye, geuing God thankes for
the benefit of Matrimony. In the ſelfe ſame councell it is alſo written.
Let not Clarkes approche the Theatre, or matia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to gape after Pageaunts:
they maye be at Mariages, but after the ſingers and Harpers be come in, who
ſerue for daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, aryſe they and depart, leaſt by theyr preſence they
maye ſeeme to allowe and approue that wantonneſſe. In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of
<hi>Illerden,</hi> holden vnder <hi>Simmachus</hi> and <hi>Hormiſda</hi>
Popes, and king <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke,</hi> the ſame is decréed: that
Chriſtians ſhould not daunce at weddinges. In the Councell of
<hi>Arriſidoren,</hi> which was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pope <hi>Deus dedit,</hi> this
ſéemeth to bée reſtrayned to Clarkes: for there is, there a
Prouiſo, that no Clarkes myght in the <pb facs="tcp:183665:28"/> feaſte eyther ſinge
or daunce, as if to others it were after a forte lawefull.</p>
            <p>Of the ſame opinion are the ſcholemen of the Diuins in the
<hi>3.</hi> Senten. Diſtinct. <hi>37.</hi> Who referre theſe reſtraintes
vnto the hollye dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rycharde</hi> of the middle Village, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth it a moſte
grieuous ſinne, to daunce on the hollye dayes as though on other dayes it
might be permitted; But farre waightere is the iudgement of the Fathers and
ſounde Councelles, then theſe mennes; Whoe hurtfullye ſet at large
thoſe things, which are to be kéept in, ſeing they haue with them
the hazard of ſoules, and not the hazard onely, but the ſlydings and falles
moſt grieuouſly to be lamented<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And yet theſe men ſéeme to
borrowe this theyr Sentence, wherby they denye dauncinge on the hollie daies of
the ciuill lawes, in the Code forſoothe, in the title of holly dayes, and
lawe holly dayes .C. tit. <hi>deferijs</hi> L. <hi>dies feſtos.</hi> We let
at liberty vacation on the holly daies, but we will that men be reſtreined
from inordinate delectations. And therefore it ſhall not be lawfull on the
hollye dayes to vſe dauncinges, whether they be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall <pb facs="tcp:183665:28"/>
or prepared for ſenſuallitye.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aemilius Probus</hi> in the life of <hi>Epami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nondas,</hi>
ſaieth, that ſinging and dauncing amonge the <hi>Romans</hi> were ſmalie
regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when among the <hi>Gretians</hi> they were had in great
eſtimation. <hi>Saluſt</hi> in his <hi>Catilinaria</hi> weighteth that
<hi>Sempronia,</hi> a certeine lewde and laſcinious woman, was trymlier
trained vp in ſinging and dauncing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſéemed a honeſt
Matron. And in the ſame place, he callteh theſe twoo inſtrumentes of
exceſſe in carnall pleaſure. <hi>Cicere</hi> in the third booke of his
offeces, is of this minde, that an honeſt &amp; vertuous man, will not daunce
in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concours of people, though he might therby become y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greteſt
heire in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. And in his oration, which he made after his returne to the
<hi>Senate,</hi> hee termed in remoche <hi>Aulus Gabinus</hi> his aduerſarye
O trickſye dauncer. It was layde in <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Murena</hi> his diſhe as a
faulte, that he daunced in <hi>Aſia:</hi> with the ſame alſo was kinge
<hi>Deiotarus</hi> hit in the téeth. <hi>Cicero</hi> for <hi>Murena</hi>
aunſweres, that no ſober per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon daunceth, eyther in ſolitarines,
either in an honeſt and moderat banquet, except he be out of his wittes. The
ſame <hi>Cicero</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:183665:29"/> in his Philip. among other vices
vpbrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Antonius</hi> with dauncinge. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth furthermore, that
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men of the Eaſt and Weſt were not of like diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: they being
of a merye minde and nimble bodies, ſo much the more delight in dauncing. For
to let others paſſe, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> daunced in open ſight.</p>
            <p>And they which now trauell to vs out of <hi>Syria,</hi> teſtifye
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Chriſtians which inhabite thoſe Regions, vpon the daye of the
Lordes reſurrection, and likewiſe vpon other famous Feſtiualles, come to
the Church with harpes and Harmonie, ſinging pſalmes and dauncing togyther.
For thoſe ſpyrites of thoſe people are quicke and quiuer, where the
ſprrites of our Countrye men are heauy and lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe, yet for al that, they
reporte that they daunce diſcretlye and modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the men and women one
from another. (⸫)</p>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:183665:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
